PCA, amounts to finding a new and special basis for your dataset.
PCA 会从数据集中发现新的特殊基
But hang on, what does it mean to find a new basis?
发现新的基是什么意思？
I'm guessing that you've heard about and even done this yourself before.
我猜你可能听过这个词 甚至之前这么操作过
But before we move on, let's just briefly review exactly what this means.
但是在继续之前 我先简单回顾下基的含义
Let's return to thinking about vectors as directions in space,
我们将向量看做空间中的方向
and start in the 2D plane.
从二维平面开始
You know that we can represent a point living in the 2D plane with two coordinates.
你知道 我们可以将二维平面中的点用两个坐标表示
The coordinates tell you how to get to the point from the origin.
坐标可以告诉你如何从原点抵达该点
For example, the vector 1,2 means go one unit to the right,
例如向量 (1,2) 表示向右移动一个单位
and two up to get to this point.
并向上移动两个单位后抵达该点
So, we see that we can decompose
我们可以将
the overall movement represented by the vector into two movements;
向量表示的总体变化分解成两个变化
one to the right, and one up.
一个朝右 一个朝上
Once we know the directions to go,
知道变化方向后
we can specify how far to go in each direction.
我们可以指定朝着每个方向移动多远
Towards this goal, let's write down two vectors,
为此 我们写出两个向量
i hat and j hat.
i 尖和 j 尖
The first one, we write as 1,0 which means move one unit to the right.
第一个写成 (1,0) 表示向右移动一个单位
The second one, we write as 0,1 which represents moving one unit up.
第二个写成 (0,1) 表示向上移动一个单位
Our original vector is made up of one i hat and two j hats.
原始向量由一个 i 尖和两个 j 尖组成
We can write it as 1 times 1,0 plus 2 times 0,1 or 1,2.
可以写成 1 * (1,0) + 2 * (0,1) 即 (1,2)
In other words, our vector can be written as a linear combination of i hat and j hat.
也就是说 这个向量可以用 i 尖和 j 尖的线性组合表示
We call i hat and j hat a set of basis vectors for the 2D plane.
我们将 i 尖和 j 尖称为二维平面的一组基向量
A set of vectors is a basis for a space,
满足以下条件的一组向量就是空间的基向量
if no vector in the set can be written as a linear combination of the others,
这组向量中的所有向量都不能用其他向量的线性组合表示
and any vector in the space can be written as a linear combination of vectors in the set.
并且空间中的任何向量都可以用这组向量的线性组合表示
If we want to express this using matrix multiplication,
如果用矩阵乘法表示的话
we could write it this way.
可以写成这样
Now, we see that the number in the top position of this vector means how much of i hat,
这个向量上面的数字表示有多少个 i 尖
or how much of the first basis vector.
或第一个基向量有多少个
While the number in this bottom position means how much of the second basis vector.
而底部的数字表示第二个基向量有多少个
So, 1,2 is how we write our vector in the i hat, j hat basis.
所以 1 和 2 表示有多少个 i 尖和 j 尖基向量
Although we use i hat and j hat most of the time,
虽然我们通常使用 i 尖和 j 尖
there are other bases we can choose for the 2D plane,
但是二维平面还有其他基向量可以使用
because there are different ways to get to our point.
因为抵达这个点的方式有很多种
We could shoot out over here,
可以先到这里
and then go back over here.
然后回到这里
Remember, that our choice of basis also effectively
注意 所选的基向量
sets up a coordinate grid for us to represent our vectors in.
决定了表示向量的坐标网格
We are used to seeing a grid made up of square boxes,
我们习惯于使用由方框表示的网格
the usual X, Y coordinate system,
也就是通常的 (x,y) 坐标系
with the basis vectors i hat and j hat.
基向量为 i 尖和 j 尖
But if we use these red and blue vectors as our basis vectors,
但是如果使用这个红色和蓝色向量作为基向量
a more sensible grid would be made up of these parallelograms.
那么更合理的网格将由这些平行四边形组成
Thus, we can represent our original vector with a different combination of basis vectors.
所以我们可以用不同的基向量组合表示原始向量
We can think of this as another language for writing down our original vector,
可以将其看作表示原始向量的另一种语言
because we see that we can write down a new set of
因为我们可以制定一组
instructions for creating the original vector.
创建原始向量的新规则
Now, all we need is a way to translate between the two languages,
现在只需一种在这两种语言之间转换的方式
the original language, where we use i hat j hat,
分别是使用 i 尖和 j 尖的原始语言
and this one with the blue and red vectors.
以及这个使用蓝色和红色向量的语言